<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Version Control on Ottmar’s Notes</title>
    <link>https://ogobrecht.com/tags/version-control/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Version Control on Ottmar’s Notes</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <managingEditor>ottmar.gobrecht@gmail.com (Ottmar Gobrecht)</managingEditor>
    <webMaster>ottmar.gobrecht@gmail.com (Ottmar Gobrecht)</webMaster>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 31 Jan 2021 20:45:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://ogobrecht.com/tags/version-control/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Download BLOBs with SQL*Plus</title>
      <link>https://ogobrecht.com/posts/2020-01-01-download-blobs-with-sqlplus/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>ottmar.gobrecht@gmail.com (Ottmar Gobrecht)</author>
      <guid>https://ogobrecht.com/posts/2020-01-01-download-blobs-with-sqlplus/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Have you ever tried to spool/download BLOBS with SQL*Plus? Some months ago I tried to find a way to download a collection of CLOBs or even better a zipped version of the collection as BLOB. I learned that BLOBs are not a valid datatype in SQL*Plus when it comes to the spool command. I found a way by putting the CLOBs into a global temporary table, creating an intermediate SQL script with tons of select and spool commands, and finally spooling the CLOBs one by one by calling the intermediate SQL script. It was working, but far from elegant. Also, when I was in the home office with a less powerful connection, it was slowing down the whole export process significantly.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quick start - version control for existing Oracle projects</title>
      <link>https://ogobrecht.com/posts/2019-07-20-quick-start-version-control-for-oracle-projects/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 20 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>ottmar.gobrecht@gmail.com (Ottmar Gobrecht)</author>
      <guid>https://ogobrecht.com/posts/2019-07-20-quick-start-version-control-for-oracle-projects/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Many Oracle projects still do not use version control. The reasons for this are manifold. Mostly it is assumed that the database is a safe place for the source code. With a working backup this is also correct, but in any case one loses the complete history of changes. Often in running projects there is not enough time to deal with the introduction of source code versioning, because at first sight there is no direct benefit to be seen. Who dares to take a second look under time pressure? This article wants to lower the hurdle for the introduction of a version management a little bit.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>New Major Version of PL/SQL Export Utilities Available</title>
      <link>https://ogobrecht.com/posts/2019-06-26-new-major-version-of-plex-available/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>ottmar.gobrecht@gmail.com (Ottmar Gobrecht)</author>
      <guid>https://ogobrecht.com/posts/2019-06-26-new-major-version-of-plex-available/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;PLEX is a PL/SQL package with export utilities - see &lt;a href=&#34;https://ogobrecht.github.io/posts/2018-08-26-plex-plsql-export-utilities/&#34;&gt;this post&lt;/a&gt; what it can do for you. In the past it was dependent on APEX for two reasons: The APEX_EXPORT package to allow exporting an APEX app and the APEX_ZIP package for compressing the resulting file collection to a zip file.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;After the first public release of PLEX, I got a comment like &amp;ldquo;Nice tool, but I don&amp;rsquo;t use APEX&amp;rdquo;. I thought I should make PLEX independent from APEX to allow at least the export of all the schema DDL and also the table data. Some weeks ago Jürgen Schuster contacted me to try out PLEX for an switch from Subversion to Git for one of his customer projects. It turns out that PLEX was not able to export the schema DDL because of errors from DBMS_METADATA regarding many Java classes. And the second issue was that one of their machines had no APEX installed. This was the final trigger for me to rework the implementation of PLEX.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>PLEX - PL/SQL Export Utilities</title>
      <link>https://ogobrecht.com/posts/2018-08-26-plex-plsql-export-utilities/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 26 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>ottmar.gobrecht@gmail.com (Ottmar Gobrecht)</author>
      <guid>https://ogobrecht.com/posts/2018-08-26-plex-plsql-export-utilities/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;PLEX is a standalone PL/SQL package with export utilities. It was created to be able to quickstart version control for existing (APEX) apps. It currently has two main functions called &lt;strong&gt;BackApp&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Queries_to_CSV&lt;/strong&gt;. Queries_to_CSV is used by BackApp as a helper function, but its functionality is also useful as a standalone. This post is all about BackApp, which has the following features:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Export the app definition of an APEX app (splitted files and optional single SQL file)&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Export all ORDS modules from the current schema&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Export all object DDL from the current schema&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Export table data into CSV files&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Provide basic script templates for export/import of whole app for DEV, TEST and PROD&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Everything in a (hopefully) nice directory structure ready to use with version control&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Return value is a file collection of type plex.tab_export_files (it was apex_t_export_files before PLEX version 2) for further processing&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Each file in the collection is represented by a record with two columns&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;name&lt;/code&gt; of type VARCHAR2(255), which is in fact the file path&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;contents&lt;/code&gt; of type CLOB&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;You can optionally zip the file collection with the helper function &lt;code&gt;to_zip&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Also see the my previous post on &lt;a href=&#34;https://ogobrecht.github.io/posts/2018-07-25-apex-export-and-version-control&#34;&gt;how to handle the apex_t_export_files type returned by the APEX_EXPORT package with SQL*Plus&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;getting-started&#34;&gt;Getting Started&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/ogobrecht/plex/releases/latest&#34;&gt;Download the latest code&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Run the provided install script &lt;code&gt;plex_install.sql&lt;/code&gt; (provides compiler flags) in your desired schema - could also be a central tools schema, don&amp;rsquo;t forget &lt;code&gt;grant execute on plex to xxx&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Startup your favorite SQL Tool, connect to your app schema and fire up the following query:&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-sql&#34; data-lang=&#34;sql&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;k&#34;&gt;select&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;w&#34;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;plex&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;to_zip&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;plex&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;backapp&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;p_app_id&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;w&#34;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;=&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;w&#34;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;yourAppId&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;))&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;w&#34;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;k&#34;&gt;from&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;w&#34;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;dual&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;w&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Save the resulting BLOB file under a name with the extension &lt;code&gt;.zip&lt;/code&gt; and extract it to a local directory of your choice. You will find this directory structure and files:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>APEX_EXPORT and Version Control</title>
      <link>https://ogobrecht.com/posts/2018-07-25-apex-export-and-version-control/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Jul 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>ottmar.gobrecht@gmail.com (Ottmar Gobrecht)</author>
      <guid>https://ogobrecht.com/posts/2018-07-25-apex-export-and-version-control/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Since years it has been possible to export an APEX app definition with the help of APEXExport, a Java utility delivered within the APEX install zip file. There is also the possibility to split the file into its components like pages, plugins and so on. There are some blog postings available how to do this - simply &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.google.de/search?q=oracle+apex+export+split&#34;&gt;ask Google&lt;/a&gt;. Also the Java based SQLcl has the capability to do the export of an APEX app directly.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
